Guide to the Quiller-Couch Family Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Quiller-Couch family papers
1878-1954
GEN MSS 551
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5.68
(8 boxes)
Writings by J. M. Barrie, postcards, scrapbooks, photographs, and a toy theater version of Peter Pan related to the family of Sir Arthur Thomas Quiller-Couch. J. M. Barrie writings consist of a photograph album and manuscript storybook by Barrie, "The Pippa and Porthos," telling the story of Bevil Quiller-Couch and Barrie's dog Porthos on a walk in Fowey, Cornwall. Postcards consist of postcard albums and loose postcards, probably collected by Foy Felicia Quiller-Couch. Postcard correspondents include Bevil and Mabel Quiller-Couch and recipients include Foy Felicia, Bevil, Arthur Thomas, and Lilian Quiller-Couch. Two scrapbooks contain holiday cards, probably collected by Louisa Quiller-Couch, and miscellaneous engravings and clippings, many of which were colored by an unidentified child. Two photographs include a signed portrait of Barrie and an unidentified building. The Peter Pan toy theater includes paper cutouts and boards showing the characters and scenery from Peter Pan.
Quiller-Couch family
Barrie, J. M. (James Matthew), 1860-1937
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Frederick R. Koch, 2002.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
SIR ARTHUR THOMAS QUILLER-COUCH (1863-1944)
Sir Arthur Thomas Quiller-Couch, 1863-1944, was a writer and anthologist who published under the pseudonym "Q." Quiller-Couch wrote many novels and collections of short stories, and edited the first Oxford Book of English Verse, 1250-1900. In 1912, he was elected a fellow of Jesus College, Cambridge. Quiller-Couch was a friend of J. M. Barrie.
Quiller-Couch married Louisa Amelia Hicks (1861-1948), with whom he had two children, Bevil Brian (1890-1919) and Foy Felicia (1899-1986), whose godfather was J. M. Barrie. After 1892, the primary family home was The Haven, at Fowey, in Cornwall.
Sir Arthur Thomas Quiller-Couch had two sisters, Mabel and Lilian. Lilian married John Hay Lobban.
Quiller-Couch died at The Haven on May 12, 1944.
Scope and Contents
The Quiller-Couch Family Papers consist of a photograph album and storybook by J. M. Barrie, postcards and postcard albums, scrapbooks, photographs, and a toy theater version of Peter Pan, all of which belonged to the family of Sir Arthur Thomas Quiller-Couch, and span the years 1878-1954. The papers are housed in eight boxes (including 3 oversize boxes) and are organized into five series: Writings of J. M. Barrie, Postcards, Scrapbooks, Photographs, and Peter Pan Toy Theater.
Series I, Writings of J. M. Barrie, contains "The Pippa and Porthos," a photograph album and storybook with 24 photographs taken January 1, 1895, at Fowey, with inscription, "Dedicated to Mrs. Quiller-Couch (without her permission). The Literary matter by J. M. Barrie. The drudgery by Mary Barrie." Photographs show Fowey, two unidentified women, Bevil Quiller-Couch, who Barrie nicknamed "The Pippa," and Barrie's dog Porthos, a St. Bernard. The story chronicles a walk taken by Bevil Quiller-Couch and Porthos around Fowey.
Series II, Postcards, contains postcard albums and loose postcards, probably collected by Foy Felicia Quiller-Couch. The postcard albums are arranged chronologically and the loose postcards are arranged alphabetically into places, people, and other postcards.
Postcard subjects, in both the postcard albums and loose postcards, include many cities, towns, and buildings across England and Europe, particularly France, Germany, and Italy. Postcards also contain pictures of animals, humorous and holiday illustrations, ships, sailboats, artwork, and people, including a series of female "Cinema Stars," English royalty, and others.
Postcard albums contain both blank and written postcards, including postcards sent to Foy Felicia, Bevil, and Arthur Thomas Quiller-Couch, Lilian Quiller-Couch (Mrs. John Hay Lobban), and Juilles Couch, an unidentified family member. Most correspondents are unidentified but include Bevil Quiller-Couch and "Aunt Mamie" [Mabel Quiller-Couch?]. Most of the loose postcards are blank, but include postcards sent to Foy Felicia Quller-Couch, Lillian Quiller-Couch (Mrs. John Hay Lobban), and Juilles Couch.
Series III, Scrapbooks, contains two scrapbooks. The first scrapbook is labelled "Arthur Couch" and spans the years 1878-80. It includes forget-me-not, Valentine's Day, Christmas, and New Year's cards from Arthur Quiller-Couch and others, possibly collected by his wife, Louisa. Manuscript notes identify some of the correspondents. The second scrapbook contains miscellaneous engravings and other pictures, many of which were colored by an unidentified child. It includes several manuscript poems, including poems signed "Sarah Ann," "Clara," "Emily," and "Elle Williams."
Series IV, Photographs, contains two undated photographs, a photograph of a portrait of J. M. Barrie, with inscription, "Yours Ever, J. M. Barrie," and a photograph of an unidentified building.
Series V, Peter Pan Toy Theater, contains cutouts and boards from a toy theater for children depicting Barrie's Peter Pan, ca. 1905. The series is arranged alphabetically into Characters, Scenery, and Other Papers. Characters includes cutouts of all of the characters in Peter Pan, including the Darling family, Lost Boys, Mermaids, Peter Pan, Piccaninny tribe, and Pirates. Most characters are represented by more than one cutout. Most cutouts are labelled with the act and scene in which they appear. Some cutouts correspond to multiple scenes.
Scenery includes both cutouts and boards representing the Darling nursery, the Lost Boys's Home under the Ground, the Mermaid's Lagoon, and the pirate ship Jolly Roger. Other papers related to the toy theater include a manuscript note by Foy Felicia Quiller-Couch, which states that the toy theater was a gift to her from her godfather, J. M. Barrie.
Authors, English -- 20th Century; Authors, Scottish -- 20th Century; Toy theaters; Fowey (England) -- Pictorial works; Photograph albums; Photographs; Postcards; Scrapbooks; Toy theaters; Authors -- England -- 20th Century; Authors -- Scotland -- 20th Century; Barrie, J. M. (James Matthew), 1860-1937 ( Peter and Wendy); Quiller-Couch, Arthur, 1863-1944; Quiller-Couch, Bevil, 1890-1919; Quiller-Couch, Foy Felicia, 1899-1986; Quiller-Couch, Lilian; Quiller-Couch family
- Writings of J. M. Barrie, 1895; Series I
  - "The Pippa & Porthos", 1895 Jan (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Postcards, 1892-1954; Series II; 1.04; (2.5 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series II, Postcards, is arranged into two subseries, Postcard Albums and Loose Postcards. Postcard Albums are arranged chronologically. Loose postcards are arranged alphabetically by Place, People, and Other Postcards. Most of the Loose Postcards are blank. Notes indicate if a folder contains written postcards.
  - POSTCARD ALBUMS
    - "Postcards", ca. 1892-1925 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Contains eighty-five postcards showing Italian art and architecture from cities including Pompeii, Rome, Venice, Verona, and others. Also includes postcards showing Roslyn Chapel and the Exeter College Tapestry. Most postcards are blank. Includes several postcards addressed to Mrs. John Hay Lobban and Foy Felicia Quiller-Couch, from Margaret Hay and other unidentified correspondents, concering art and travel.
    - Untitled postcard album, ca. 1902-05
      Contains one hundred and eighty-eight postcards showing buildings, villages and cities in England, France, Scotland, Spain, and Switzerland; various animals; humorous and holiday illustrations; advertisements; ships; artwork; and photographs of unidentified people. Most of the postcards were sent to Foy Felicia Quiller-Couch. Additional recipients include Bevil and Arthur T. Quiller-Couch. Most correspondents are unidentified, but include Bevil Quiller-Couch and Mabel Kerr. Seven postcards are blank.
    - "Album", 1904-10
      Contains one hundred and eighty-five postcards, showing villages and cities in England, France, Germany, Ireland, and Italy; sailboats and ships; photographs of unidentifed people and animals; illustrated holiday cards; and several postcards from the Franco-British Exposition of 1908. Most of the postcards were sent to Foy Felicia Quiller-Couch. Additional recipients include Bevil and Arthur T. Quiller-Couch and Juilles Couch. Most correspondents are unidentified, but include Bevil Quiller-Couch and "Aunt Mamie." Approximately seventeen postcards are blank.
    - "Post Card Album", ca. 1909-21 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Contains one hundred and thirty-one postcards showing villages and cities in England, Scotland, France, and Italy; sailboats; illustrations of children; watercolors; birds; holiday cards; and photographs of unidentified people. Most of the postcards were sent to Foy Felicia Quiller-Couch. Approximately thirty postcards are blank.
    - "Post Card Album", ca. 1909-54 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Contains fifty-eight postcards showing villages and cities in England, Wales, and Scotland, as well as a few unidentified people. Most postcards are blank. Includes several postcards sent to Felicia Foy Quiller-Couch, Mrs. [John Hay] Lobban, and others from unidentified correspondents.
    - Empty postcard album, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - LOOSE POSTCARDS
    - Places
      - Belgium
        - Brussels, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 6)
        - Waterloo, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Denmark
        - Copenhagen (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - England
        - Burell House, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 9)
        - Forder Village, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 10)
        - Great Chesterfield, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 11)
        - Hampstead, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 12)
        - Harting, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 13)
        - Hereford, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 14)
        - Ince Castle, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 15)
          Includes notes describing Ince Castle
        - Kew Garden, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 16)
        - Midhurst Sanatorium, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 17)
        - Ringmer, 1920-23 (Box 3, Folder 18)
          Includes eight postcards sent to [Foy Felicia] Quiller-Couch, signed B. B. [Bevil B. Quiller-Couch?] and one postcard to Mrs. [John Hay] Lobban, from an unidentified correspondent.
        - Treyford, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - France
        - Avignon, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 20)
        - Beaulieu-sur-Mer, 1924 Mar 31 (Box 3, Folder 21)
          Includes one postcard to Juilles Couch from N. Mitchell
        - Ile de Port-Cros, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 22)
        - Lyon, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 23)
        - Nîmes, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 24)
        - Orange, 1928? (Box 3, Folder 25)
          Includes one postcard to Juilles Couch from an unidentified correspondent
        - Paris, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 26-28)
        - Versailles, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 29)
      - Libya
        - Tripoli, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 30)
      - The Netherlands
        - De Zonheuvel, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 31)
      - Switzerland
        - Chesieres, 1921 Jan 17 (Box 3, Folder 32)
        - Territet, 1923 Mar 5 (Box 3, Folder 33)
      - United States
        - California, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - People
      - Chamberlain, Joseph, 1904 Aug 22 (Box 3, Folder 35)
        Includes one postcard to Miss L. Quiller-Couch from an unidentified correspondent.
      - "Cinema Stars"
        - Griffith, Corinne, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 36)
        - Logan, Jacqueline (Box 3, Folder 37)
        - Morgan, Marilyn, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 38)
        - Nixon, Marian (Box 3, Folder 39)
        - Shearer, Norma, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 39)
        - White, Alice, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 40)
        - Young, Loretta, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 41)
      - English Royalty
        - Alexandra, Queen, consort of Edward VII, King of Great Britain (Box 3, Folder 42)
        - Edward VII, King of Great Britain, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 43)
        - Edward VII, Funeral procesion, 20 May 1910, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 44)
        - George V, King of Great Britain, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 45)
        - George V, Coronation, 22 Jun 1911, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 46)
        - George V, Coronation Durbar, Delhi, 12 Dec 1935 (Box 3, Folder 47)
        - George V and Queen Mary's silver jubilee, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 48)
        - Henry, Prince, Duke of Gloucester, wedding to Lady Alice Christabel, 6 Nov 1935, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 49)
      - Maartens, Maarten, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 50)
      - Mackenzie, Compton, Sir, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Other Postcards
      - British military postcard, "[Blank] is Serving his King, Country, and Empire" (Box 3, Folder 52)
      - Kaleidoscopic postcard, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 53)
      - Large Alpine Daisy, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 54)
      - Sculpture, "Angel of the Annunciation," Victoria and Albert Museum (Box 3, Folder 55)
      - Raphael, "Granduca Madonna" (Box 3, Folder 56)
      - 2 watercolor postcards showing boats on rivers, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 57)
- Scrapbooks, 1878-80; Series III; 0.42; (1 box)
  Series III, Scrapbooks, is arranged chronologically.
  - "Arthur Couch", 1878-80 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Untitled scrapbook, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 59)
- Photographs, n.d.; Series IV
  Related Archival Materials note
  See also: "The Pippa and Porthos," Box 1, folder 1
  - Photograph of a portrait of J. M. Barrie, signed, n.d.
  - View of unidentified building, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 60)
- Peter Pan Toy Theater, ca. 1905; Series V; 0.42; (1 box)
  Series V, Peter Pan Toy Theater, is arranged into three subseries, Characters, Scenery, and Other Papers. Each subseries is arranged alphabetically.
  - CHARACTERS
    - Animals
      - Crocodile, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 61)
      - Ostrich, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 62)
      - Wolves, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 63)
    - Darling Family
      - John, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 64)
      - Liza, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 65)
        See also: Mrs. Darling, Box 5, folder 68
      - Michael, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 66)
      - Mr. Darling, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 67)
      - Mrs. Darling, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 68)
      - Nana, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 69)
      - Wendy, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 70)
        See also: Peter Pan and Wendy, Box 5, folder 81
        See also: Lost Boys and Wendy, Box 5, folder 73
    - Lost Boys
      - Curley, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 71)
      - First Twin, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 72)
      - Lost Boys and Wendy, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 73)
      - Lost Boys on the pirate ship Jolly Roger, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 74)
      - Nibs, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 75)
      - Second Twin, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 76)
      - Slightly, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 77)
      - Tootles, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 78)
    - Mermaids, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 79)
    - Peter Pan
      - Peter Pan, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 80)
      - Peter Pan and Wendy, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 81)
    - Piccaninny Tribe
      - Piccaninny tribemembers, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 82)
      - Tiger Lily, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 83)
        See also: Groups of pirates, Box 5, folder 88
    - Pirates
      - Black Pirate, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 84)
      - Captain Hook, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 85)
      - Cecco, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 86)
      - Cookson, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 87)
      - Groups of pirates, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 88)
      - Jukes, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 89)
      - Mullins, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 90)
      - Noodler, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 91)
  - SCENERY
    - Columns, [ca. 1905]
    - Curtains, [ca. 1905]
    - Home under the Ground, [ca. 1905]
      Includes the wood above
    - Kennel, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 92)
    - Lamps, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 93)
    - Mermaids' Lagoon and pirate ship Jolly Roger, [ca. 1905]
      The pirate ship Jolly Roger is on the verso of the Mermaids' Lagoon
    - Nursery, [ca. 1905]
    - Proscenium arch, [ca. 1905]
    - Rock, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 94)
    - Row boat, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 95)
    - Trees, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 96)
    - Water and rocks, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 97)
    - Wooden toy theater base, [ca. 1905]
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Envelopes, [ca. 1905] (Box 5, Folder 98)
    - Note regarding Peter Pan toy theater by Foy Felicia Quiller-Couch, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 99)
- Oversize, 3.6; (3 boxes)
  - Untitled postcard album (in Series II), ca. 1902-05 (Box 6, Folder 100)
  - "Album" (in Series II), 1904-10 (Box 6, Folder 101)
  - Photograph of a portrait of J. M. Barrie, signed (in Series V), n.d. (Box 7, Folder 102)
  - Columns (in Series V), [ca. 1905] (Box 7, Folder 103)
  - Curtains (in Series V), [ca. 1905] (Box 7, Folder 104)
  - Home under the Ground (in Series V), [ca. 1905] (Box 7, Folder 105)
  - Mermaids' Lagoon and pirate ship Jolly Roger (in Series V), [ca. 1905] (Box 7, Folder 106)
  - Nursery (in Series V), [ca. 1905] (Box 7, Folder 107)
  - Proscenium arch (in Series V), [ca. 1905] (Box 7, Folder 108)
  - Wooden toy theater base (in Series V), [ca. 1905] (Box 8, Folder 109)